SANCHIT SHARMA

y twitter.com/sanchitsharma85 in linkedin.com/sanchitsharma98 🕠 github.com/sanchitsharma

Experienced Software Engineer, Team Lead and Architect with 6 years experience in product conceptualisation and building distributed service oriented architecture at a fast paced startup.

TOOLS & LANGUAGES

Programming Languages

Proficient - Python. Familiar - Java, C++. Web Technologies Django, Javascript, Flask

Databases PostgreSQL, InfluxDB, Worked with Druid

Data Analytics dil pandas, numpy

Communication **Protocols** HTTP, MQTT, Modbus.

DevOps Ansible, Grafana, Docker, Kubernetes **Cloud Environments** Azure, AWS, GCP

Others Kafka, Airflow, Redis

EDUCATION

CGPA 8.12, B. Tech. (Computer Science)

IIIT-Delhi

2009 - 2013

91 %, XII CBSE

Jaspal Kaur Public School

2008 - 2009

85.8 %, X CBSE

Jaspal Kaur Public School

2007 - 2008

PROFILE SUMMARY

Joined Zenatix - an IoT startup as employee #1 in Nov 2013. It was acquired by Hero Electronix, a Hero group company in May 2018. Now a 100+ people organization with 12 people tech team.

Owned product development based on customer and internal needs. In 6 years, gained experience in developing, maintaining IoT applications, Django based web applications and cloud data pipeline. Worked with the co-founders and a cross-functional team of data scientists, designers, operations and support. Optimized hiring process while recruiting 8 software engineers in 12 months within a constrained budget.

EXPERIENCE

Software Architect, IoT Cloud Group

Zenatix

April 2018 - August 2019

Q Gurugram, HR

Architected and led cloud side of development. Developed growth culture in tech team and incorporated best practices for development, meetings and work reporting.

- Kafka Based Data Pipeline Architected and led infrastructure development for MQTT ingress at scale into Kafka for streaming, archival and analytics.
- Monolith to Microservices Led the breaking up of a monolith into 8 Django based services talking to each other over REST.
- o ORM for sMAP ORM over query layer of sMAP (proprietary timeseries database) as a Django library. Formed the core of most services in the stack.
- WattMan Configurable dashboard for customers to consume reports, key metrics and alerts.
- o Control Deployment Module Dashboard to deploy automation actuation rules across 100's of IoT Gateways.
- Error Reporting Developed a Diango library for logging and reporting of domain specific errors.

Technical Lead, IoT Cloud Group

Zenatix

April 2015 - March 2018

♀ Gurugram, HR

Built and mentored a team of 7 developers. Responsible for providing a roadmap and subsequent delivery of IoT Cloud stack.

- Following frameworks were designed to enable data science team in deploying their code for customer/internal use cases -
 - Alerting Real time stream analysis on incoming (single or group of) timeseries and sending notifications via email/sms.
 - **Reporting** Framework to enable data-science team to add new python functions/classes as reports which could be mailed or shown on dashboard.
 - Metrics Framework to make computed timeseries using code by combining and processing existing timeseries based on business use case.
 - Issue Reporting For interpreting problems in devices on fields based on the health timeseries data reported by them.
 - Led the dockerisation of existing services.
- Device Management Platform Cloud + edge modules for monitoring, versioning and updation of software/configuration in IoT Gateways. Mentored in design and implementation.

Software Engineer

Zenatix

Zenatix

Movember 2013 - March 2015

♀ Gurugram, HR

- o Developed and maintained from scratch -
 - Energy Web App Django Web app for visualising data trends, analysis, reports and alerts, forming core of the various products sold.
 - Data Collection Module Modular framework for adding new sensors.
 - Scheduling Framework Framework for automated actuation of devices/sensors handling complicated edge cases.
 - Edge Health Module Scripts for reporting health of networking, cpu et al. metrics of IoT Gateways and self-healing.
- Forked open source repos and deep-dived into the code to fix production stalling issues
 - readingDB Timeseries database built on top of Berkley DB.
 - sMAP Archiver, data collection and query framework for timeseries data built on top of reading DB.
 - OpenWRT Compiled a custom image of the open-source OS with custom scripts to work in Zenatix routers (deployed live in more than 1500 locations) blog-post